Never forget why you are the church.
But in Romans 11, we continue.
But more specifically, We are looking at
why we believe in eternal security through
salvation by faith in Jesus Christ.
We're going to recap from last week.
If you weren't here last week, I'm not going to be able to preach to you all these points,
but we are going to recap, for us to lose our salvation,
there are some important things that would have to happen.
Now understand something.
I understand that this is a very, very deep topic, a very
deep point of discussion.
It's a theological debate that has been had for many,
many more years in just the last 2 weeks.
Amen?
And I'm going to try to answer as many questions as
you have through the preaching of God's word, but there are going to be questions
you have that I don't answer today.
All right?
That's why we are to learn about God increasingly, not just in
church, but increasingly, everywhere we go, but I do think
that is an important doctrine to understand that
when you are saved, we use this one saved, always saved,
a lot of times it's a slur.
Well, they believe and once they always say, and they can do whatever they want.
Listen, that's not what I'm saying.
That's not what scripture says.
Let me remind you again of Romans 6.
Do we sin more just to show off grace?
Paul says, God forbid.
May it never be so.
Don't ever let somebody excuse a
doctrinal position by other people not
truly understanding the word.
All right?
We need to go to God's word for this.
But here's the thing.
If we were not eternally secure,
let me just tell you something, you will never make it.
Because we're sinful.
We are by definition unholy and wicked and vile.
Yes, you, and yes, me.
So this is important.
So some major things would have to happen if we were to lose our salvation, major things.
Miraculous things.
First off, God would have to destroy the new creation.
Look at 2nd Corinthians 5.17.
Therefore, if any man be in Christ, he is a new creature,
old things are passed away, behold
all things are become new.
In doing so, listen, yeah, you have to understand something.
When God says that old things are passed away, that means
they cease to exist.
Now, listen, do I completely understand how we are
still in the flesh and we battle the flesh, we do battle the
old man, although he is gone, but listen, we have the victory
through the new man, through the new creation in Christ.
We are completely made new.
We are not a revised version.
We are not a remodeled version.
We are not an improved version.
The Bible says we are a completely new creation.
As a matter of fact, the Bible says that ye must be born
again to go to heaven.
Right?
Now, listen, again, in doing so, he would have to revive the
old creation, which is right there a contradiction.
How do we revive what has never had life in the 1st place?
Ephesians 2 says we were dead in our trespass and sin.
So how do you revive that which is dead?
And there's no evidence in scripture to see that this can happen.
God would have to destroy the new creation and he's not going to do that.
If we were to lose our salvation also, though, God would have to revoke
his purchase, one Peter 118 and 19,
for as much as ye know that you were not redeem or corruptible things, as
silver and gold from your vain conversation received by tradition from
your fathers, but with the precious blood of Christ.
Now let's connect that, for as ye know that you were not redeem a
corruptible things, but with the precious blood of
Christ, as of a lamb, without blemish and without spot.
That word redeemed means to rescue,
to ransom, to set free, to liberate from
an impressive condition.
There is no more oppressive condition than the condition of being
lost and a slave to sin.
How does God redeemers?
Well, we were set free by our ransom being paid through the blood of Jesus.
Listen, this transaction is final and eternal.
God does not revoke purchases he makes.
Listen, anyone ever been a sprouts?
Anyone ever?
No, don't go.
I'm telling you.
So listen, I have this mindset now and I share too much, but I'm wanting
to get my protein numbers up.
You know what I'm saying?
And so I'm getting carbs and sugar.
Man, I got that.
Thats on lock.
Amen, you know what I'm saying?
Like I ain't got no problem with carbs and sugar.
I got to get my protein up.
And so we were like, you know what?
We're gonna do some meal prep, and I said, you know, my uppity sister
over here, she goes to sprouts all time, and I was like, you know, I'm gonna try sprouts.
So I went to sprouts, and, man, we bought all kinds of chicken.
I mean, it was amazing.
The store is absolutely phenomenal.
I loved it.
By the way, right after we left there, for meal prep, went to Domino's and got some pizza.
But anyway, so listen, Saturday night, you know what I'm saying?
You got to do what you got to do.
But let me just tell you something.
We're getting there and we're getting stuff that we feel like is regular stuff.
I mean, we're looking at.
Look at some chicken.
We looking at some orange juice.
We're looking at some, man, they got this, like, chocolate milk that looks really good, so I got
the little in the glass jar.
I mean, I just feel like, like a, like, you know, little house in the prairie, you know what I'm saying?
Just, like, pouring milk from a glass truck, all the thing.
we get to the where you check out.
And so we had the, we had the, 1st off, they charge you
for the bags.
That's dumb.
Dude, I don't want to charge you for everything else, and then you had the audacity to
charge me a dime for each bag.
Anyway.
So, and we had a lot of bags.
We're sitting there, and we're going, and see, my wife,
she does the groceries, so that's, like, her thing, and she's, like, looking at me mad
as fire, because I'm the one that said, we got to go to sprouts, get healthy, amen?
Get that air chill chicken, not that frozen chicken.
And man, it's going up, and I was like, this, this is, and I started sweat.
And I'm sitting like, oh, this is not good.
So I'm just sitting there.
And I feel like I don't know if someone just kept on throwing things in the buggy.
But it would never end as we started, you know, be,
be, there's always something to beat.
You know what I'm saying?
Like it was, we got them, and it was like 200 something
dollars, and we were only prepping for 3 days.
We got in the car and Heather wasn't talking to me.
I said, Heather baby, you okay?
She said, not yet.
I said, this is what we'll do.
I said, if we do this, we can never go back.
Just know, if we do what I'm about to say, we can never go back to sprouts ever again.
Let's go back and return everything.
Obviously, we didn't do that, amen?
That's not what you do.
Listen, as silly and dumb as that illustration was,
Let me just tell you something.
God is not going to revoke or return the
eternal purchase of your soul.
Amen?
It's not going to happen.
Once he buys and redeems you, it is done.
If we were to lose our salvation, God would
have to revoke our pardon.
Romans 5, verse one, therefore, being justified by
faith, we have peace with God through our
Lord Jesus Christ.
God would have to go back on his pronouncement
and declare us unrighteous again.
Remember, being justified is to be pronounced
and declared by God, righteous in his eyes.
That is something that he does.
We don't deserve it.
We don't earn it.
It is through faith in Christ Jesus.
Church, this does not match the character of God.
we see in scripture to revoke that pronouncement.
It's not going to happen.
If we were to lose our salvation.
God would have to break his promise of eternal life.
1st John 2.25
And this is the promise that he hath promised us, even eternal life.
First John 513.
These things have I written unto you that believe on the name of the Son of God, that
you may know that ye have eternal life, and that you may
believe on the name of the Son of God.
His promise is a yes and amen through Jesus Christ.
Now, that's just a review.
We're going to look at 2 more things that we're going to go over.
Then we're going to go back to Romans 11 in order to bring it all together.
When a person becomes saved, understand my strategy here of teaching this.
I'm not necessarily looking at every nook and cranny to
prove to you how you cannot lose salvation.
What I'm doing is I'm trying to teach you what happens when you obtain salvation.
And so when you obtain salvation, you understand how eternal
and how permanent it is, okay?
So that's how I'm doing this last week and this week.
Are y'all with me saying, amen.
When a person becomes saved, God seals them.
I would hope that you know this one.
I've talked about it a lot, but we're looking at the concept of eternal security.
Let's pray.
Father, I thank you, Lord, for this word.
God, I pray you give me power, clarity, and liberty, liberty to preach your word this morning.
God, I pray those that have ears to hear, may they hear.
And God, I pray that you give us comfort and encouragement, God.
build us up.
God through your truth.
In Jesus name, we pray.
Amen.
We won't take as long again on this point because we talked about it recently in
depth, but I love the clarity that we get from Ephesians chapter
one, starting in verse 13.
in whom he also trusted after that ye heard the word of truth.
The gospel of your salvation, in whom also after that ye believe
you were sealed with that Holy Spirit of promise,
which is the earnest of our inheritance and to the redemption
of the purchased possession unto the praise of his glory.
There's 2 words you need to understand when we
talk about our salvation being sealed.
Sealed and earnest.
Those 2 words, write them down if you're taking notes.
We were sealed with the Holy Spirit of promise.
This is speaking of the Holy Spirit of the living God.
That word sealed means to mark in a secure manner.
to deliver safely.
In other words, we have been marked by the Holy Spirit.
He is going to deliver us safely to heaven as we go.
Amen?
That is what the Holy Spirit does for us.
If that's not permanent enough for you, look at the next word earnest.
Again, Ephesians one, verse 14, which
is the earnest of our inheritance, until the redemption of the purchased
possession, unto the praise of his glory.
The NASB 95 uses the word pledge,
who is given as a pledge of our inheritance,
with a view to the redemption of God's own possession,
to the praise of his glory.
What does an earnest payment include?
Well, if you look at what it means in the Greek,
it means a 1st installment.
A deposit, hear me, which guarantees,
everyone say guarantee.
A sure down payment.
Everyone say sure.
A pledge.
For us to lose, hear me, for us to lose our salvation.
God would have to take back a pledge that
served as a guarantee of the purchased
possession, which is our soul.
Well, pretty sure why wouldn't God do that?
God can do whatever he wants.
Well, exactly, but he's also tied to his character.
God can do nothing that is contrary to his character.
That's why God can't sin.
Because God is holy, holy, holy.
Amen?
That's why when we look at scripture in our own view of
life and view of morality and view of righteousness,
We get sometimes confused that why God does the things he does.
It's because his character is perfect both in his love and in his wrath.
We can't understand it because we're not God like he is.
Amen.
So we see here, why would he not just
take back the payment, right?
I'll give you another thing that I did one time.
Anyone ever remember, we moved into our house.
Listen, I'll be trying to make some purchases.
I'm just realizing this.
Anyone ever heard of rain soft?
The water filtration system.
No, good, good.
Good, good.
They came to my house.
Heather was pregnant with river, okay?
There you go, Will, I mentioned River, as I preach.
She told me I was going to.
Evidently, I mentioned my girls all the time when I preach.
It's just part of it.
I'm gonna mention three girls here soon, but whatever, okay?
But I was at the house, he comes in, we're gonna get a free
Home Depot gift card.
Amen?
Y'all know what I'm talking about?
Let me just come look at your water, and we'll settle up.
I'm like, man, come on, look at the water.
And you know how you do in your mind?
Man, he can come over here all he wants, dude.
Iin't buying nothing, right?
That's what I had in my mind.
There's no way.
I'm a salesman too.
You were a salesman, salesman.
You can't get me.
Oh, he got me.
You know what I'm saying?
He got me good.
He started doing this little thing with the water, and I don't know how in a...
You drink tap water, you are disgusting.
That's gross.
Get you some get you some Kroger drinking water, okay?
Get you some aquafina.
But listen, so I'm sitting here thinking, this is what he says.
Man, you don't want your new baby to be bathing and drinking this water.
I sure don't.
I got to provide for my family.
So I'm sitting here and I'm like, look, okay, here we do.
I was like, man, I just bought this house.
I don't even know I can afford this house, but I just bought this house.
But I can tell you what, I can't, I can't afford this, but I, I need, I have to have this.
And so I said, here's what I'm gonna do.
I'm going to do a little down payment on it.
And we're going to get things rolling, but I got to figure some finances out,
but I don't want you to leak.
I want this deal.
You know how they do.
He got me, got me, got me, okay?
Just know, don't look at me stupid.
I know it's bad.
But he got me, man, listen.
As he left, I started looking up some stuff.
You know how you do when you leave.
And then the next day, I called him.
I said, Hey, man, listen.
I said, you have every right not to do this.
But I need that check back, dog.
He said, what do you mean?
I said, I need that check back.
I mean, you can keep it if you want, but I'm going to need it back.
And so if you could just tear it up and put void on, it'd be great.
You know what he did?
He did it for him.
But let me just tell you something.
That is not how things are supposed to go.
Hey, man.
When I gave him that check, I was fully, and I asked for
it back, and he gave it back, praise the Lord.
But I was fully responsible for what I paid.
Listen, when God guarantees by
indwelling the Holy Spirit within you, that is a sure
down payment, an installment into the age
of redemption when he comes back and gets us.
He is not going to change that.
He's not going to take it back.
But why would he not do that?
Well, look at the end of Ephesians chapter one, verse 14,
to the praise of his glory.
Our redemption brings him glory.
By the way, may I interject here something important?
How does this take place?
What had to happen in order for
God to put his eternal mark on us?
Well, we read it in verse 13, in whom ye also trusted,
after that you heard the word of truth, the
gospel of your salvation, in whom also after that you believed you
were sealed with that Holy Spirit of promise?
We heard the gospel.
We believe the gospel, therefore, we trusted God,
the result, we are saved and sealed.
Why am I emphasizing this this morning?
Nowhere is it mentioned about works.
Nowhere is it mentioned about rituals or tradition or baptism.
Here, believe, and trust.
That's how he becomes sealed.
Amen?
Romans 10, is that it should sound familiar.
I'm going to read you some scripture that you should know.
Romans 10 verses 9 through 15 that thou shalt confess
with thy mouth, the Lord Jesus, and shalt believe in thy
heart that God hath raised in from the dead, you will be saved.
For with the heart, man believeth unto righteousness,
and with the mouth, confession is made unto salvation, for the scripture
saith, whosoever believeth on him shall not be ashamed, for
there is no difference between the Jew and the Greek, for the same Lord overall
is rich unto all that call upon him.
For whosoever shall call upon the name of the Lord, shall
be saved.
How then shall they call on him in whom they have not believed,
and how should they believe in him, of whom they have not heard, and how should
they hear without a preacher?
And how shall they preach, except they be sent as
it is written, how beautiful are the feet of them that preach the gospel
of peace, and bring glad tidings of good things?
This is all to God's glory.
There is a, you believe, you confess with your mouth.
Jesus, you are Lord.
I believe in my heart that God raised Jesus from the dead 3
days after Calvary.
The Bible says, you will be saved.
And it's to his glory.
Speaking of glory, when a person becomes born again,
The 5th thing we're going to look at, we are promised glorification.
Remember what we learned in Romans 51, moreover, whom
he did predestinate, them he also called, and whom he called,
then he also justified, and whom he justified, them,
he also glorified.
Notice Paul writes this truth in the past tense, although
we have not been glorified yet.
Obviously, we're here in these bodies.
It's because our salvation as sure as it is good is done.
What is glorification, though?
That word glorification in the Greek has 3 primary senses.
I want to read it to you so you understand.
The verb has 3 main senses.
The majority of occurrences refer to believers,
verbal praise offered to Jesus Christ or
God in response to promises, miracles, and saving acts of deliverance.
In other words, in this sense, this word refers to ascribing
glory to our or magnifying the greatness of the higher being.
In other words, when we were worshiping this morning,
we were glorifying the name of Jesus with our mouths.
Does that make sense?
That's what we do.
That's why it's so important to sing.
That's why when you stand there and you're not singing, you think, well, I just don't sing in public.
Well, here's the thing.
If there's ever a time to sing in public,
It is to glorify Jesus with your mouth.
Amen.
But I guarantee you this, if I put on your favorite country song.
Or if I put on some critics, Clearwater, or if I put on some Motown,
or if I put on some eagles, I bet you some of you guys that ain't never sung in
church, be like, oh, snap, and you start singing, why?
Because you...
You see where I'm going with this?
Listen, if we're ever going to become more
undignified, may it be as we worship the Lord with our lips.
Are y'all with me this morning?
That's the 1st sense of glorification, right?
The 2nd sense captures how a person's deeds or
entire life can glorify God when carried out with love
and obedience to the will of God.
That is one's actions in themselves can be said to glorify
God when they are guided by his will and carry it out in order to please him.
All right?
So in other words, Jesus and the Holy Spirit's salvific
actions can be said to glorify the Father.
How we live, not just what we say, can glorify the Father.
You know where there's power in, there's power in your proclamation
on church on Sunday, matches the life you live Monday through Saturday.
That's what the world's looking for.
That's a good way to share the gospel is to
praise his name and glorify him, but also match your life
in obedience to him.
The issue is we have a lot of people that come to church and glorify
the name of Jesus, but then live like hell the rest of the week.
Listen, that's not how God called us to live.
And by the way, you're not the exception.
You say, ah, well, you know, I just have my, you are not special.
God has a plan and it includes each and every one of us.
If you're born again, we just talked about it.
You'll be changed.
Y'all with me?
But the final sense of this word, Doxazo describes
the transition of God's children into an exalted
eschatological state of Doxa after the resurrection from the dead.
Now, I just said a lot of things right there.
In other words, when the end time happens, I
believe Jesus is going to call us home and when we rise up with him and
become called up, we're going to have glorified bodies.
And as believers too, will enter into this state of
glory, a promise so secure that it's described as in some sense
already accomplished.
That's how secure it is.
For us to lose our salvation, God would have to break his promise of
a future glorification, even
though he describes it as already done.
Y'all with me this morning?
Don't lose me.
Now God is not a liar.
So what does scripture mean then?
We're going to go back to Romans 11.
That's what happens when we come saved.
All right?
So why did we even bring this up?
That's a good question.
All right, Romans chapter 11, it talks about being cut off from the tree.
We had to look at this from every angle possible.
See, in the gospels, Jesus taught that there are wheat
and tears, literally he is making a distinction between the saved
and the lost.
In this parable, it is the enemy who planted terrors amongst the wheat.
So look how Jesus explains this in Matthew 13,
27 through 30.
He says this.
So the servants of the householder came and said unto him,
sir, this not thou so good seed in thy field.
From whence then hath it tears?
He said unto them, an enemy hath done this.
The servant said unto him, wilt thou then go?
We go up and gather them up, but he said, nay, lest while ye
gather up the tares, you root up also the wheat with them.
Let both grow together until the harvest, and in the time of harvest,
I will say to them, the reapers, gather ye together 1st the
tears and bind them in bundles to burn them, but gather the
weed into my barn.
Notice the timing here in the harvest.
What does this have to do with being cut off?
I'm going to read.
I don't have it here, but you should have it in front of you.
I forgot to put this in, AVT.
My apologies.
But in Romans chapter 11, verses 19 through 22,
this is what it says, okay?
That will say then.
He's speaking to the Gentiles.
The branches are broken off that I might be grafted in.
Well, because of unbelief, they're broken off, and thou standest by
faith, be not high minded, but fear.
For if God's spirit not the natural branches, take
heed lest they also spare not thee.
Behold, therefore, the goodness and severity of God on them which fell severity,
but toward thee goodness, if thou continue in his goodness,
otherwise thou also shalt be cut off.
Now this can bring up a problem for some people.
What do you mean cut off?
What do you mean I'm hearing that I'm not?
Is he teaching that we can lose the
salvation that we have?
Well, remember, for you to lose your salvation, so many crazy
and miraculous things has to happen.
So it cannot mean that.
It is actually quite obvious.
Those who not continue in the faith are cut off from
the promises of God.
In Romans 11, Paul is doing 2 things.
He is teaching that instead of being arrogant in our faith,
we ought to rather understand our fragile state
aside from God and have a posture of reverence
and humility towards God.
Secondly, he teaches that the fakes will be exposed.
In 2004, John Piper said this regarding Romans 11 and being cut off.
And I enjoy the way he explains this.
When he gives a threat like don't become proud, don't boast over
the unbelieving Jews because otherwise you too will be cut off.
The true believers take it to heart and stand in all.
In other words, there's a fear and respect and reverence towards that.
It's kind of like the difference when I was growing up,
All Mama had to say is, I'll go tell your daddy.
And all of a sudden, I would straighten up.
You understand what I'm saying?
Because I knew what that meant.
Y'all with me?
They tremble at how fragile they are and how dependent on grace they are.
and how crucial their authenticity is and how urgent
it is that they prove real in their behavior.
In this way, the threat serves to keep them from falling.
Now, I don't want you to miss this.
I did some research on wheat and tears.
During the early stages of growth, they look almost identical.
That's why farmers don't go out and
try to pick out the tears because because they look so similar,
they're going to pick out some of the wheat as well.
I want to say this.
Does that not also teach eternal security?
Are y'all with me?
In other words, Jesus said, hey, the guy said, no,
don't go out there right now because if you pull some up, you might pull some of
the wheat, and that's not how we operate.
Amen?
So during the early stages, they
would not separate them.
But then the harvest got there and that's when they began to look different.
They may look the same in the early stages of growth, but at a closer,
but closer to maturity, there is a stark difference in posture.
See, a tear will stay upright.
In other words, they'll be nice and tall.
They actually have a little bit of black fruit in
the top and it's actually toxic and empty.
It doesn't do any good for anybody.
But it's so light, it's so empty.
It's so vain that they just, they stand straight up tall
all the way to the harvest.
But a wheat's different.
Y'all ever seen wheat out in the field a little bit too long?
What does a wheat start to do?
Well, the longer it gets to stay in,
The longer until harvest.
It begins to get heavier and heavier from the time it begins to bow low.
The longer you keep it out there, the lower it bows.
You picking up what I'm putting down right now?
See, a terror counterfeit believer will live life standing up in
pride thinking they got it all under control.
So they're sitting here in arrogance thinking, hey, I've
got everything like I need.
I'm good.
I've done enough good.
I do this, I do that.
I'm fine.
Let's go.
But the fruit that they're bearing is empty and toxic and vain.
But a wheat, on the other hand,
A wheat, on the other hand, will bow low.
A true believer is what the picture is will bow low in humility.
Why?
Well, the grain on the top of a wheat becomes so much
that they cannot bear it.
Let me just tell you something.
God has blessed me so much.
that I should not be able to bear it in my life.
to the point to where because I know who the blesser is,
I live my life bowing down to him.
And in doing so, our posture will expose the fakes.
Y'all with me?
But this will not be known until harvest time.
where the true believers will endure.
This is what many call the perseverance of the saints, and I
believe this is a biblical stance that must be understood.
You say, what about all these people?
Well, just because someone calls themselves a Christian?
does not make them a Christian.
Judas was counted among the 12, yet he did not persevere.
His heart was never set on Christ, but rather money and earthly things.
He was part of the ministry.
He was treasurer for the group.
He did all the things.
He saw and partook.
He was even at the last supper.
Yet he left.
See, Paul understands how important this is to know.
2 Corinthians 13, five, test yourselves.
to see if you are in the faith.
Examine yourselves, or do you not recognize this about yourselves,
that Jesus Christ is in you unless indeed you fail?
The test?
I want to say this here because it's very critical to comprehend.
Now, I want to, I want to, to
preach this and declare this with grace this morning.
I know why this is a tough truth to both explain and understand.
There are many here today who have loved ones.
Friends, children who you care about.
But they fall into 2 categories.
Regarding what we're talking about today.
They fall into 2 categories.
One, they may profess to know Christ, yet all their actions speak otherwise.
Hear me today, church.
You don't have to say a word and the way you live speaks plenty loud enough for you.
That's why the church is not being taken seriously today.
Because we take the freedom that God has given us as a gift.
as a tool to be used for him.
And we use it for our flesh.
So when the world looks looks at us and we
proclaim Christ with our lips, but our life does
not match the proclamation, that is not confusing.
I've said it before, that is very clarifying to a lost person, that's fake.
We live in a world with a lot of fake, amen?
We live in a world to where you look at something and now with the AI and
all the things that are going on, you don't know what's real, what's fake?
Let me just tell you something.
If anything this world needs to be real, it's the believer in Jesus Christ.
The Bible makes it very clear.
You know them by their fruit.
A good tree bears good fruit and a bad tree bears bad fruit.
Now this does not mean that a good tree won't have a rotten apple every now and again.
Amen.
You good trees in here.
Have y'all ever sinned, since you've been saved?
Of course you have.
That's a rotten apple.
That's a rotten fruit, okay?
And it also doesn't mean that a battery can't produce a good apple every now and again.
You do understand, and there's whole denominations far from God that
do not know Jesus, that do a lot of good things in this world.
That doesn't mean I'm going to heaven.
Y'all with me this morning.
I'm trying to tell this with grace.
But it is not hard to tell the difference between a good tree and a bad tree.
Well, I just don't feel like I have the right to judge.
I hear you, but I hear Jesus louder, amen?
Look at what he says in Matthew 7.
Beware of false prophets, which come to you in sheep's
clothing, but inwardly they are ravening wolves, yet ye
shall know them by their fruits.
The men gather grapes of thorns, or figs of thistles, even so every good
tree bringing forth good fruit, but a corrupt tree bringing forth evil fruit.
A good tree cannot bring forth evil fruit, neither can a corrupt tree bring forth good fruit.
Every tree that bringeth forth not good fruit is hewn down and
cast into the fire, wherefore by their fruits, ye shall know them.
Now, I know what you're probably thinking.
if you're really paying attention.
Well, pastor contextually, Jesus is warning against false prophets.
So I'm not trying to teach.
I'm not trying to preach, so that doesn't apply to me or the regular person.
Well, let me ask you this.
The principle is repeated and broadened in Matthew 12, verse 33, is it not?
It says this, either make the tree good and is fruit good or else make the tree
corrupt, and is fruit corrupt, for the tree is known by his fruit.
Here, Jesus speaks of the hypocrisy, the Pharisees.
By the way, the Pharisees were supposed to be those who were closest to
God and the most godly, yet they were rotten inwardly.
Does this not sound like many professing Christians today?
What we have done is we replace sound biblical
doctrine with this thing called emotional theology.
Well, preacher, they say they love Jesus.
I don't want to offend them.
Maybe they just see things differently.
That's exactly why you need to open their eyes to Christ that is truth.
You do understand just because they believe differently doesn't make them right?
They need to know what God says about it.
I was listening to what's
to do with the scientist.
Neil DeGrassi.
What's his name?
Is that it?
Neil DeGrassi?
Listen, I watched the whole video on the way home yesterday.
I just want to see how smart this guy really was.
And I'm not, listen, I'm not a physicist.
I'm not a scientist.
When I went to college,
I went for concrete.
You understand what I'm saying?
Some of the easiest stuff ever.
But so I'm not the smartest person in the world.
But the way he was explaining all this.
Listen, someone calls him the smart one of the smartest people in the world.
He goes to the White House.
He talks for the scientific community.
Yet when you really look at it, all the
objections he has about the word is
actually laid out within the word, and he's proving the
word by rejecting the word.
Yeah, I missed that.
And I cannot say it again like that.
So you're gonna have to just catch it again, okay?
Listen, what I'm trying to say is this.
In his rejection of the word, he's proving the validity
of the word, God said, this was exact, the exact thing happening.
God said it would happen.
The exact objections, God said, he calls it, man, it's foolish to play this way.
Exactly.
God said he used the foolishness of preaching to
turn those who are wives.
Do you see what I'm talking about here?
But listen, we got to understand, just because someone disagrees.
does not mean, oh, okay, well, you do your own thing.
Listen, I care too much about people to just let them do their own thing and end up in hell?
We've got to tell them.
Or an excuse I've heard too many times, and I'm so sick of it.
Because I'm so sick of this excuse.
Are y'all with me this morning saying, man, my goodness gracious.
This is what they say.
Well, they got issues just like me.
So, who am I to judge?
Well, don't that sound good?
Get right with God and tell them.
Well, they have so many issues and just like me.
So who am I to even point out their sin?
Get right with God and rebuke their sin.
Did y'all miss it the 1st time?
We sit here and we say, oh, well, I mess up.
And so what I God tells us to live holy as he is holy.
We don't excuse their sin for our sin.
We get right with God and we declare to them the gospel of Jesus Christ.
Brother or sister, to that, I say, get right with God and
share the gospel with them.
Scripture tells us the fruit they bear makes it known where they stand.
Someone has to offend them.
Someone has to tell them that Jesus is not
an idea or a cultural safety net.
He is savior and Lord.
And their sin is deserving a condemnation, therefore, they must be
forgiven by the blood of Jesus.
In other words, stop excusing the sin and lostness of the people you
care about and give them Christ.
By the way, what is the risk?
If they are saved through your rebuke, they may be convinced to turn back to Christ.
Repent of their sin and move back.
If they are lost, they may be born again.
Sounds like a win-win to me.
To you?
Amen.
But then there's the other category of people.
What about those we care about who started off well?
They were in church.
They know the Bible.
They had made a public profession of faith, but now they are far from God.
They have all but denounced Jesus.
Or maybe they have fallen to a lifestyle of habitual sin.
What about them?
This is where I believe it hurts the most.
But I believe God is the most clear on this one.
First John is often called the Book of Assurance.
Whenever someone is having trouble with their salvation, whether or not they will
go to heaven, I advise them to carefully read 1st John.
John has some strong truth for those who seem to have fallen away from the faith.
He says this in 1st John 2.19.
They went out from us.
But they were not of us.
For if they had been of us, they would no doubt have continued with us.
But they went out.
that they might be made manifest.
In other words, known that they were not all of us.
Pastor Adrian Rogers says it like this, a faith that fizzles before the
finish was flawed at the first.
Church is very clear.
those who partake in the faith, those who have been made new, purchased, redeemed,
justified, and as good as glorified, they will
continue in the faith.
Not saying they won't have bad days or bad seasons, but they will continue.
What about those who die in a state of stumbling?
There are many places in scripture that where God says those who
practice sin will not inherit the kingdom of heaven.
That word practice or commit, brings a meaning of
ongoing pattern of sin in a person's life.
We would call this habitual sin.
Now understand something.
This is speaking of a lost person.
We know that if you're born again, nothing can separate you from the love of God.
So we know that even if you if you stumble and fall,
And you somehow leave this world in that state of stumbling,
whether it be, hey, you know what, let's just use a simple illustration of
you're speeding down the road, you're breaking the law, you get into an
accident, you broke the law, you did wrong, you sinned, you know you were doing it.
What, you just go to hell?
No, no, no, no, no.
If you are born again, nothing can separate you.
Y'all with me.
So, so, so it's not that you die in a state of stumbling,
because the state that you're in eternally is covered by the blood of Jesus.
The saved person has placed their faith in Jesus, has the blood of Christ put on their account.
They have been saved.
They are saved, and they will be saved from the wrath to come.
That's what scripture tells us.
So how do you handle a person who has obviously fallen away?
Well, you treat them as they are.
Lost and in need of Jesus.
This morning, here's the truth.
You cannot lose what you never had.
Y'all with me?
And you cannot lose what you haven't earned.
A gift is non-conditional.
A salvation is a gift from God.
If there was anything we could do to lose salvation, then our
eternity would be contingent on our performance rather than God's promise.
And let me just tell you something.
If your salvation was contingent and dependent on your performance, you done lost it.
So what do we do?
One of the most convicting chapters in all the New Testament, I believe, is in Ephesians five.
It clearly outlines what it looks like to persevere.
By the way, I want to, I want to just kind of inform you on something.
Do not let These lost
people that don't know Christ, but like to talk about Jesus, define
how you should live your life.
There's this thing going on to where we're allowing people that obviously
don't know the true Christ.
They might know religion.
They might know all the do's and don'ts, they might
know how to put you in a corner in a negotiation
or a debate, but they don't know Christ.
They're not they're not regenerated.
They have not been saved.
And we're taking their opinion, we're taking their perspective.
More than we are God's truth.
I'm not going to let the world define what a Christian looks like.
Period.
Because let me just tell you something.
What what we look like?
is opposed to the world.
The Bible literally tells us, hey, they hated him.
They're gonna hate you.
If you have a faith that is well and
beloved and liked and tolerated
and all things, then you probably need to re-look at your faith.
Your faith in Jesus, we'll
offend the world at some point.
Y'all with me?
So what does it look like?
I'm going to read you some scripture.
not in the screen.
I going to read it just straight from the Bible.
This is how, listen, if you're confused, if you're doubting.
If you're discouraged in your faith,
I believe this outlines right here.
Therefore, be imitators of God.
As beloved children and walk in love, just
as Christ also loved you and gave himself up for us, an
offering and sacrifice to God as a fragrant aroma.
But immorality.
Or any impurity, or greed must not even be named among
you as is proper among saints, and there must be no
filthiness and silly talk or coarse jesting, which are not fitting, but
rather giving of things.
For this, you know with certainty.
that no immoral, impure person, or just man who is an idolater.
has an inheritance in the kingdom of Christ and God.
Let no one deceive you with empty words.
For because of these things, the wrath of God comes upon the son's disobedience.
Therefore, do not be partakers with them.
For you are formerly darkness.
But now you are a light in the Lord.
Walk as children of light.
For the fruit of light, consist in all goodness and righteousness and truth,
trying to learn what is pleasing to the Lord.
Do not participate in the unfruitful deeds
of darkness, but instead even expose them.
For it is disgraceful, even to speak of the things which are done by them in secret.
By all things become visible, but all things become visible when
they're exposed by the life, for everything that becomes visible is light.
For this reason, it says awake sleeper.
And arise from the dead and Christ will shine on you.
Therefore, Stay with me here.
By the way, this is how they preach back in the day.
They read God's word.
God's doing a pretty good job at saying what he's trying to say.
You hear me?
Therefore, be careful how you walk.
Not as unwise men, but as wise.
Making the most of your time.
Because the days are evil.
So then do not be foolish, but understand what the will the Lord is.
And do not get drunk with wine.
For that is dissipation, but be filled with the Spirit.
Speaking to one another in psalms and hymns and spiritual songs,
singing, and making melody with your heart to the Lord, always
giving thanks for all things in the name of our Lord Jesus Christ the God,
even the Father, and be subject, be subject to one
another in the fear of Christ.
Let me explain something to you.
A lost person.
If you're doubting your salvation.
What are you desiring in your life?
A lost person will come to church, they have no problem doing that.
Especially the music's all right, and the preacher says a few things, it's funny.
They'll go to church all day long.
But we're talking about some deeper things in that chapter.
He's setting the standard little higher than just coming to church and leaving.
See, this right here to persevere like this requires
the Holy Spirit, a living God.
So let me ask you, how you walking?
How are you walking?
Here's what I don't want to do today.
And we're almost, we're basically done.
Someone's saying, man.
Here's what I don't want to do today.
Wesley used this on Wednesday, I guess his thinking, here's a humongous.
So it's been moving all day long.
Can y'all hear me?
You good?
Two things I don't want to do.
First off, I don't want to confuse those who are saved and try to make them doubt their salvation.
That's not my job.
That's not my role.
I don't ever want to do that.
But I can tell you this, ever since I've been saved, I never doubted my salvation.
Now sin has caused me to have a separation.
But I've always known that I had the injury on the Holy Spirit.
Now, before that, I doubt it every single day.
But it wasn't necessarily a doubt, it was just an understanding that I'm lost in
need of Jesus, and I'm just not willing to put my faith in him.
I'm enjoying my sin.
I'm going to stay in my sin.
But when I got born again, I'm a new creation.
I don't want to confuse you today.
But a 2nd thing.
Y'all hear me here.
I will not.
Attempt to let you be lost.
and continue in your sin, and falsely declare him as Lord.
I want to clarify.
God's word clarifies.
So if you're born again, praise the Lord.
Let's walk as a light because he is light.
The days were evil.
lets not waste time.
Let's serve them together.
People say, I don't need a church.
You do realize the ending of that talks about the fellowship of the believers.
But if you're here today,
And you think just because you walked an aisle,
Just because you said some prayer and repeat it after some pastor.
Just because you know all the right lingo and no, John
316 because you learned it as a kid.
But there's no fruit in your life.
that looks like Jesus.
Test yourself today.
Examine yourself.
And you know what I believe?
Through faith in his word, the Holy Spirit will clarify it for you.
I pray you don't fail the test with hezban eyes closed over this place.